so we're here in Hyde Park this is the
first of what I hope is going to be a
ongoing series known called the common
ground so what I'm going to do each week
is I'm going to find two people from
different walks of life in some way
different nationalities different races
religions whatever it might be and just
a discussion between them about things
that affect their lives things that
bother them things they think about in
particular we're going to try and focus
on you know broader societal issues but
wherever the conversation heads this
week we've got Dave on the left is Dave
he's he's london-based he's a part of
the zeitgeist movement he's the London
organizer for the church site guys
chapter there and on the right is
Swedish is that right yeah a Swedish
chap that we've met here today by the
name of Christian who's got some very
interesting ideas very interesting
things to say so hopefully this will be
an interesting conversation and let's
just start off with you've been hanging
around for a couple of hours now
Christian what particularly has struck
you about what you've heard today you
know conversations that you've had with
people whatever work what what are you
going to take away what are you going to
take away from today
when it comes to the increasing
difficulty of actually being just a
normal person in the society because of
the increase in death and that is to
maybe like you can't really live an
ordinary life in our large city as
London and you might have to move out
take a step outside of London and maybe
live in a smaller city or maybe move
abroad to Spain and like create a life
there would you be my real life decide a
bit more with me my real life just you
know making life as you want to live not
really the only thinking about how to
make your money and how to survive the
day and if you if you want to like all
your house you have to Spain spend the
thousands of thousands of dollars or
pounds just to be able to live in an and
then you have to work all day long and
you will be exhausted
you will miss like good times with your
family and this is what I've seen when I
do some research that this is more like
the common ground
of people like both in Sweden but also
in u.s. I was recently there and they
all kind of said that I have to work
harder and longer to actually earn a
little bit less each year and the
housing me just keep housing prices
chief just growing and growing and like
it doesn't really stop and that's what I
mean like I want to have just a normal
life being able to care for what I
really care about that is becoming more
and more scarce or harder to come to as
a big concern for me because I want to
live my life purposefully I don't want
to work away
in order to be able to breathe as a word
with you absorb perspectives from from
the zeitgeist moving even you've been
involved with these ideas for quite some
time now and so yeah what if anything is
suck you today so you put quite new
people anyone said anything to you
questions that they came up with or
ideas and they have that stuck with you
well I've been so these ideas out the
last seven years or so and it is
actually the same arguments all over and
over again you know what's about read
what about corruption what about people
are more deserving and others things
like this and I I say that really they
am really big shine work sites good
photos compassion quite difficult what
we have
you know it's very different system
natural law resource based economy is
where people have access rather than
property
we can do that gradually at the time
how long it take you know there was
enough galvanized ocean people behind
these ideas of collaboration sharing it
could happen you know actually 100 maybe
150 years if we measured our shits Kelly
so I know I won't say it my life um it's
not about me is about
employers change because something to be
said for that
yes so the system we advocated is
basically directly type of resources the
natural limitations
so
we need the economic systems directly in
line natural resources and human needs
noticed our human needs are how they can
be met most refugees the sustainable way
possible
this could be done by calculation Peters
don't agree
trying to about it may be incredibly
hard leads noble recently we have
exactly how many but the long-term goal
of survival species is the main goal
there we need to have work pieces we
have how to using the most efficient way
possible you say that women can feel a
bit more about the idea of access versus
properties yeah so basically we could
talk transitioning them as opposed we
could have surprise sensors we can read
towards a rental system where you're
gonna to exchange money credits or part
or anything like that you just have a
surprise Center we have 3d printers
where you can actually make things one
of the Mars and it's beautiful we can
make the marker 3d printer officials
make things directly then there you
don't have to do this duplication of all
this stuff the load of warehouses
powerful sources share with swipe things
on the mark and make it highly efficient
and medium please and once no lot we
bring up once or lock if you say war if
I want ten Ferraris or what do I would
wear if I want Africa is my backyard so
I'm really stupid like that then I would
say to them that well you know it has to
take revolution and values as well it
doesn't matter what I actually wanted
what the earth provide for us that is
basically what needs to happen library
need to have a value system that's
completely in line with any natural
limitations are doping we need to
restrict if we could provide everyone
the highest and move it
structural sense focus you know so
severus world so every fruit out itself
it needs to be a global initiative basis
make this happen because resources
scattered everywhere no man is an island
Oh coach are we're an island but no we
can't operate like that because we
especially the UK between for everything
but yeah it needs to be global change
now I was thinking about that you know
having I want to see ten Ferraris and I
was Africa the back yard
I mean you doing basically if you have
access to that you already have you have
act Africa as your backyard because you
have had and if you have access to ten
for ten different forests you actually
have access to ten different roars you
can just go borrow in the morning you
can borrow like a 1970 Ferrari and then
like 11 or 11 in the evening you can
pour another one for purpose doesn't
really win when it comes to access you
have access to everything I think that's
the problem because now we think
our ownership you think you come from an
ownership thinking that's why you ask
that type of question every time you buy
your but you don't really need it
whenever innovate and that that stay
that the mental shame to happen you have
just beyond the barriers of having
people be cover needs to be restriction
of something otherwise and people who
totally advanced the situation but
really I mean even the for water meters
first came about if it still turned off
of it you might be accustomed anything
to do so if they knows that dumb
thing to do then turn off you know it's
just irresponsible so you know I think
people can be responsible for resources
things that you know more free
I think libraries have been example that
had an ice age came before them really
cost anything they still return respect
we can actually take that concept and
apply to other things gradually
see here baby
and also like people focus a lot of
thought of the products hold the order
that we can have like a library but we
can also have a library of imagine if we
connected all the engineers like all the
professional photographers and they
together produce the perfect app and
that's just storing the collaboration
within certain fields of science and for
example in sugar or music and we do will
I be able to actually produce something
that is profoundly better than today
imagine the air imagine the board
innovators or the engineers actually got
together make the best back cameras at
the world and really you know we only
need about five different cameras in the
model I overcame we actually evocate a
collaborative design system where all
might work the same thing
fully open source so you can see a
project online build upon it and others
can build upon it just made it so
efficient that's why the innovation of
this is actually Skylar to be no limit
to see magical program should actually
take joy in programming and expend hours
in their rooms
just in programming environment imagine
if that energy went into action created
because that actually materialized to be
amazing moving
[Music]
just be amazed the progress and also
like doing as a lot masculine about the
test that we really need to decide I
mean everybody works like that
would have a problem
product at all we will probably see
through design obsolescent element in
the bottom of I phones and other
computers and
stuff like that
we could start focusing and repairs
actually gaining a trust in the product
but also trust in the system we would
start taking care actually be careful at
store like if we had this phone or you
have it for 10 years at 20 years because
we will maintain it we would actually
probably start thinking about other
stuff than how the brothers design we
will start thinking about
[Music]
some reading will actually stop talking
instead of talking like about maybe
things that are only like
has no value professor we have to come
into ourselves or baggage musings about
and actually tell our interest lovers
might have the opportunity to do that
two hours a week however they define
sick man Italian a sixth exhausted so we
used to work to elaborate system system
where you only have to work two hours a
week you'll be amazing
interesting back to the obsolescence we
are talking about this farsighted really
intrinsic plan this five based cream the
deliberate withholding the efficiency so
to repeat purchases
please action more insidious because
former minerals in the ground to the
shelves of the shop was actually the
middleman little egg creaming off the
top so by the time it gets a shot
everything's a piece of because
it's just so inefficient because it has
to go through this process in the market
do you have any concerns about explain
well it's the transitions I mean I know
it's really hard to actually come up
with the proper transition because all
the systems are so different how I do
actually do that
so that that's one concern we just have
to work toward those you have but how do
you do today when it comes to the death
do you as person do you use crypto
currency or justice like I kind of
promote that or how do you like they go
it's a possible transition steps and I
think how many local currencies I think
that could be a good chance it'll just
disorder may be stabilized and so they
saw people working closer together in
communities this may pinch every slaver
as a whole have
so sporadic as it is now and I mentioned
time bacteria inside time backs straight
out so I do my doing things
I suppose there was the lone country a
moment about there if you have a small
country rich in resources out to be
socialist they could be the first wise
the government was disabled we were
advocating actually the first tested to
demonstrate and shown all over the world
[Music]
be like Google Maps based on what the
lack of I so basically like final way
now what formative each solar what
intentions are there you know how cities
be laid out most efficient most
iniquitous way offered possible it is
demonstrate our conferences shown to
government and they could have just just
the doctor to take the idea just make it
happen
I read a little bit about the penis for
the UI
he has the wrong City
pick everything up go away with it
why
[Music]
sweet and we're kind of talking about
that type of system during the
we're starting thinking about creating
like 99% of the new buildings that's
real today we can actually recycle and
break down with all the material
somewhere else
and on their way but that's not really
talked about by now there's more talk
about living by the profession and the
company
I think
we need to some way like a knight in the
government creating those types of rules
so not just one company and does it so
so that all the kinda stuff ability
we need to use less resources there may
be more recycle but there's the problem
right now that the cement is actually
soaring to decrease in availability
that's a big problem
whether they like turning to bamboo when
they're starting to use that but you
can't really build a building
this is a big problem so it's a way
along the line we have to have rules but
it feels that the government is so
just the same way of having new thoughts
against digital boss
it goes on back I don't know how we
actually can go along how we can create
laws for the future for strength for
sure me in terms of transition
we try to make profit and building a
brand new city that's highly efficient
from the ground up it's hardly any money
in them
so
work outside the offices I think the not
for the military of the military is an
example how they do operate outside our
systems are so externally though these
technologies are made so in the you ship
or something oh sorry they just make it
happen because it's they wanting to
happen so they've put the body into
resources pray
city staff
[Music]
so the concept is that we habitus it is
terribly it takes too much many
resources too much time and energy so it
just make sense to let me do it
something
so what if we come up with a system that
is perfectly efficient for for example a
small city up to 5,000 people then you
have another like open I can
have so much amount of building as well
so much amount of vehicles like this
will change from the amount of
inhabitants per city would it be very
very boring if we had I know you may go
back to can your people imagine is very
cold the clinical everything staff noise
standardization is very efficient or
understanding the spirit for I would say
now argument you can rip hold just that
one percent efficiency the good thing to
the variety I think that map
and many designs but I think efficiency
Wayne angel of grade six own faces own
efficiency where's our plane plane copy
made on the other way because it has the
flyer
I have to go through the air so it can't
be pricey but what more is I don't know
if you have that who will actually
decide of how much percent we will
decrease the efficiency who will decide
how the location
make sure you can use the algorithms but
somewhere you have to you have to take
in the human part
[Music]
build a city that is for humans to live
in sure that's not mean in the first day
you need to be counted what happen
culture nor the things that required to
make these functional fossils prospers
possible can be taking it with her
having the things were very so open and
it's changeable like we basically have
so multi-purpose or building functions
where's not specific there while there
are provide work churches with a sex
tape
basically a wall and then it's not me
out exactly i interchange big wheels and
cradle spaces really quickly so fans
could happen within the same space
strictly comedy today so happy
I think culture is just as important as
everything else part young
so enjoy themselves
very social really find ourselves and by
comparison
taken into account
but this system will order that with me
because the resources are destroyed so
it's like to shine or keep them and
Sweden their resources because we have
enough pain
well I think that these sources can be
trapped rabbit the mana Traxxas and
resource allocator where most of the
population population be calculated
[Music]
calculate out for the amount of world in
cities you need to build and possible
so that's all taken into again
we'll be sort of showing probably so
is this what they called human
[Music]
technology when they for example they
left a
a professional racer
son
they roll around on the track here they
censor everything in the tension in the
wheel
so they gather all that data they put it
in a computer that augmented the perfect
measles for that title track yes
that's what you're feeling and the
perfect thing yeah you can even get a
way to do this Intel the AI system a boy
there you want to over tear that thing
probably come up with come up with its
own design before how what's the most
efficient way of educating
as I said you say senses local well
giving us the data and they can go to
the e centralized cities and is no one
controls everything another one for a
decentralized system still Italians the
grantee they can be more decentralized
Amman so essentially planned in the
sense that there is information flow
resources that need to be come in
calculation consensus page given city
skills and a penis - there's a range
that way they'd want live just work I
think you know
they got the ability to do
the majority of the world
maybe there are a few people that really
like sometimes walking they were
probably have to say
yeah
[Music]
I study boy
Kenichi is shown and if their jobs that
are really hated in that designing why
not buy the payment
an incentive for active work
sorry I hate to bust into a conversation
with sterling most shitty jobs if
society is all on the same page all
working for the same goals most shitty
jobs can quite easily be automated
aren't they Thanks so you know what I
mean IIIi think this whole shitty job
thing is a bit of an argument because
almost every city job I can think of is
pretty easily automated you know it
wasn't for the threat of people losing
their jobs if we were to automate all
this stuff it would have been done long
ago you know what I mean so yeah I think
it's kind of a non-starter that argument
about who's going to do the season job
example case there is something that we
can try that people be shitty that's why
the air bag overstated technology
you see automated bars main Brits so you
also see hoses could also like cleaning
you can fit and cleans where I was
talking to some lady about how robots me
to recruit and I think about that could
have a rocketing famine robot needs to
be intricate in the shade the colors
racially the backyard if they do exist
you go by some state technology and one
what's really frightening like your
letter in your question what's really
frightening is that few people that have
the capital
we'll use this they will use the
machines to benefit themselves and what
we see now we see like 40% of the tools
that we create your here is actually
throwaway way because you know we
actually juice the juice that 40% in
perhaps selling it for of the value or
maybe given away the price of the goods
that they're actually selling from
because people would use that with
people will buy that product then will
buy it when it's kind of also like
thinking about companies are storing too
boring stop
and for other types of fishes and we
have done a lot of gears now they're
forming that they're forming execute
this is a bit worrisome for me as well
because
if you own the food
if you are so rich that you own so much
of the show you can just voice it all
the other laugh and feel like be able to
produce like form vicious of food and
sell its expensively to other people
that will actually sustain the
economical system today to actually
we have known and
I really like word that we'd love going
on
what it looks like is scarce today is a
good system like if something is scarce
that's worse
happily through food or water from -
that's a good I want to right before it
pops cares
to another destination before
that's what
I don't know how to do with that I don't
see any problem
[Music]
transition but the change has come
somewhere and I say to people that you
know so that wasn't a point system if
it's too far head or they'd ever seen a
concrete
I'm sure they pulled that about slavery
2,000 years ago sorry
look at the same thing answers
to
the society so
the hardest engine suppose something new
you might cover though you know that I
mean the zeitgeist me tried to galvanize
over the years we recognize that it
might not necessarily be the same ice
cream it might be another key it might
be change my campus somewhere else
one that will provide you have it back
of my mind
fifty-fifty step-by-step process I think
like a basic income fix all the
humanitarian lives all together
greetings
[Music]
surely
and she tried to make this happen
and even in Tanaka through the civilians
who marches
like that they call it Brandon
basic encompass my form I'm not green
with a resource-based economy they can
all agree on my scheme so that's one
step then we want to achieve that then
we can move on
preowned as well
I said watch their faces Island now I'm
very whether they're consistent with
their beliefs is very specific steps
really make everyone aware of
listen like what I heard about basic
income is that kind of it could be
another
[Music]
they show
because
you all agree if we all agree that this
that the basic income should be one
thousand all about or for each person
but after a while the goods and stuff
that you need to pay for actually
increase but
for example if you have the same
government that we do today it's really
hard to change them basically from you
because then they will talk if they do
today like where should the money come
from who should pay for that you already
have the basic income why are you gonna
bar and it could be another type of
slavery slave system we are probably a
better one that we have days but where
we have to like also
go beyond that beyond that as well
absolutely
that's why the FK is a long-term
solution it hasn't so common to even the
elite the wealthy actually an
application little bit themselves they
know people that are spending on their
stuff yeah that so it's not a solution
or yourself reason why I advocate is
because it is going to help the most
desperate the most people very
desperately the people that I work I
really need to survive somehow but also
for their like that the middle laugh
because if you work hundred percent you
can actually with baking and you will
probably good up to victims maybe work
for out and then create the product that
that you really like I've thought about
you want to create them that could be in
a
good for mankind I think of all the
brains out there that you that's not
really me is put to good use because of
the hacker work we have less time at
work and more time and actually develop
ideas and innovation
actually except he's been a number of
studies actually I recommend a book
called fly by Daniel then he actually
went through all these studies that
showed that actually money interferes
with our greater pool and she gets in
the way the maze of reason
Sheldon
farmer 12
my using translators
[Music]
technology to do tasks well because
their money the point is our money Rob
be toasty
so so yeah it's an inner in
relationships I mean that the main thing
is money they argue or maybe they're all
data that I've seen that the thing that
people most order along
[Music]
awesome